Good afternoon everyone.
>> We're back here again to continue our
series on marriage and uh thank you for
coming back. Okay, let me just say
because uh you know um I need to say
this so please hear me out. Um I want us
to talk about the hard side and the hard
things of marriage.
And that includes the pain of divorce.
And as I share with you,
I just want to say that it is not my
intention to hurt anyone.
There are some of you who have gone
through terribly difficult
um situations in marriage and
particularly with divorce and
separation.
And even talking about this is painful
for you. And uh you could well say that
you know bishop you don't really know
what you're talking about. And it's true
because I've never been through divorce.
And there's a pain that comes with that
that only those who have gone through
that know what it's about. And so please
forgive me if my words are not well
chosen. The intention is not to hurt
anyone. The intention instead is to
speak with clarity especially as
concerns um that which the scriptures
call us to when it comes to this very
very hard and difficult topic. Now
having said that let me just also say
this. I think there are probably if I
could use this analogy and it probably
isn't uh you know the best of analogies
but forgive me if it's not um it doesn't
fit well. Um I think there are probably
five different levels of you know um
relationship in marriage and the first
of those is what gets you into marriage
in the first place. When you fall in
love and there are the flowers and the
perfumes and the chocolates and the
dinners and the candlelight and the you
know the emotions and being wooed one
way or the other whether it's a man or
the lady and this is the romance stage
and uh it's followed when you get
married with a honeymoon stage that you
go through. Okay, however long the
honeymoon is, you know, 10 days, 20
days, 30 days, 6 months, whatever it is.
Okay, and I want to liken that to a car
of all things. But this is a male
illustration. A car of all things. When
you get into a car, pull out your keys,
put them in the ignition, and you turn
the ignition on.
What you may not realize is the science
of starting a car is this. It is not the
key you turn in the ignition that turns
the engine. That's not how a car works.
Instead, the key you put in the ignition
and you turn
then fires the the starter in the car
that is electrically run by the battery
and it fires it up to turn and to begin
to turn the very very little turn the
crankshaft and it then fires the pistons
and the engine begins to mechanically
ally turn the crankshaft of the car.
Okay, the key does not turn the engine.
The key switches on the starter in the
car and the starter with an electrical
charge fires up so that the pistons and
the crankshaft and such can now take
over turning the engine. Okay. Now, if
you leave the key in the ignition and
you turn it and the car starts up and
you keep turning it and keep turning the
key, all you will do is completely burn
out the engine. It will burn out the
starter and do damage to your car.
You're really only supposed to flick it
and it starts the car and then you let
it go. And you all know that because
many of you here drive. Okay, that's
what marriage is like.
the emotions that accompany the the
quoting and you know the beginnings of
love as you are going out on dates are
the key fired up by the battery.
After that little honeymoon
the engine kicks in and drives the
marriage for the rest of life. Okay.
Now, there are romantic times even after
you've been married a year or two, but
for a lot of marriages,
it's really just a living together,
getting up, getting the kids to school,
you know, paying the bills, uh doing
work, maybe making a home, and all those
sorts of things. It's not very romantic.
It's just a reality that you have to
live with because a marriage needs to
take care of the kids and whatever else.
And you know, that's a marriage. Which
brings us to the second level. If the
first level was honeymoon, this is the
second level of marriage. And if you
watch my hands, it is below and beneath
the the first level. This is a
honeymoon. It's all loveydvey and
perfumes and etc. This is the mandane
daily living in marriage.
And for the majority of marriages,
marriage is mediocre and mundane.
You live in the same house.
There are not, you know, there's not
much love lost between you. There's been
too many battles and too many conflicts
and too many disagreements and too many,
you know, chest thumping and too many
angry tones and you're in it now because
you just need to finish bringing up the
kids or making a home. You live with the
hope that this will not be the rest of
your life. But for a lot of people, this
is the reality they will face the rest
of their life.
But marriage can get worse than that.
The third level down here. And the third
level is where there is such brokenness
in the marriage that it leads to um how
do I put it there? It's crushing.
There are many tears. There are many
unkind words. There are many gestures of
lack of care and concern for the one
that you married. There are many times
when anger is displayed and you have to
hide away from the anger and lock
yourself up in a room. And there are
many times when you just want to walk
away from this thing. It did not become
what you had wanted it to become and
it's just crushing your spirit and your
soul and there is no more joy and there
is no more happiness. That's a third
level of marriage and it's down here. If
this was a honeymoon and then this was
the mundane reality of just making life
all together. This is that space where
you just feel crushed and something
inside of you is slowly dying.
But there is an even worse state of
marriage. And this is when a marriage
gets to the place where there is
brutality
and there is you know unintentional
wounding even to the place where you
cannot recover
where your life is under threat.
and where you don't know whether you
should stay or you should leave.
I've known somebody in this state who
was severely beaten by their spouse and
in this case it was the wife who was
suffering the brutality with two
children and the children were also
brutalized
and very early in my ministry you know
the wife came and saw me and told me you
know what makes this even worse is not
just the beatings and the brutality it
is that my husband husband is a police
reservist and there is a gun in the
home.
And many of times in the night he'll
come home and he will pull out the gun
and he'll be waving it around and it's
loaded and you'll be threatening us with
it.
And I told her, "You need to leave.
You need to leave."
And when marriage gets to this stage,
then the brutality forces us to face the
question of separation
or the question of divorce.
And these two the Bible actually talks
about
the really thorny side of separation and
divorce is not the separation itself.
The Bible does say that if you do need
to separate for a while, yes, for the
matter of prayer, but come back
together. But then there is a divorce.
And the Bible tells us that Moses
allowed for divorce because of the evil
of your hearts.
The really thorny issue is having been
divorced. What does the Bible say about
remarrying?
I talked about divorce last Sunday. I
did not talk about remarage and we can
come to that at a different time. Okay?
As opposed to in this series.
These are four different levels where
marriage is broken and marriage doesn't
work. But there is the hope of one level
that goes beyond the honeymoon
into a marriage that is fulfilling and
nurturing and beautiful.
But I will tell you about this state
here that is better than the honeymoon.
It takes real effort and hard work to
have this. It is achievable. It is there
and it can work. He is still broken. But
there is a place where marriage is
fulfilling and beautiful and faithbuing
and nurturing and all the things that we
hope for in marriage, even though we're
still broken. But it takes hard work.
You have to put in the time and the
effort to be able to enjoy this. And the
hardest work of being able to achieve
this is that every day
you must die
to yourself
for the marriage to thrive.
The purpose of marriage
is that I would die. Somebody has said
that God uses marriage like a toilet
brush to clean the inside.
And it is painful.
But the only hope that you can ever
achieve this side of marriage is you
have to be willing to put in the hard
work. And the hardest work is that I die
daily
for marriage to thrive.
We're going to be talking about that
dying daily next Sunday and what it
takes to die daily
for today. Having said that, I want to
use an analogy that I intimated to last
week but that I want to explore a little
more because if we do not realize this
truth and embrace it, we will never
really have the uh the opportunity to
build our marriages to the place where
they are fulfilling and they cause us
energize us and they fill us with some
measure of joy. And for that I need to
go back to Genesis 3:1 17 through to
verse 19. We looked at this briefly last
week. I want to explore it more. This is
when Adam and Eve
sinned in the Garden of Eden. And in
verse 17 through 19 of chapter 3,
Genesis chapter 3, God came and he said
this to the man in the garden. Cursed is
the ground because of you. Through
painful toil, you will eat food from it
all the days of your life. It will
produce thorns and thistles for you, and
you will eat the plants of the field by
the sweat of your brow.
You will eat your food until you return
to the ground itself. Work for Adam was
about tilling the ground. Adam was a
farmer
and scratching a living out of the
ground. before his sin.
Before he sinned against God,
the ground willingly gave him of its
fruit. He planted and it was maybe a bit
like the story of Jack and the beantoalk
threw out the seeds at night outside of
his window. Woke up the next morning and
this plant reaching up to heaven had
grown. Amazing.
100% return on every effort to till the
garden. But after he sinned, God put a
curse on the ground and said, "It will
no longer be productive and fruitful for
you." In other words, the ground will
never ever give you 100%
back for your labor.
Now by the sweat of your brow you will
reap from the ground and it will be hard
work and there is a built-in futility
into it and you will plant 100 seeds and
20 of them will be eaten before they
have a chance to sprout by the bugs in
the soil. And another 20 of the hundred
will be eaten by all the bugs that
appear, the you know the white flies and
all the other bugs that appear to to eat
at the succulent new shoot. And even if
they survive that, another 20 will be
lost because the weeds will grow up
faster than they and they will choke the
plants you planted so that they never
bud and they never fruit. Another 20
will be eaten up by the uncooperative
weather. The rains didn't come. There
was a, you know, hot blaze of sun and
everything died. And then another 20
will be eaten by the birds before you
have a chance to harvest. And you will
sweat and you will labor and the ground
will not willingly give you its fruit.
This is what your sin has done. Now, not
many of us are farmers here today. There
are some, I would believe, but not many.
So, that language may not apply for you
or you don't understand it. But the
curse still applies to all work fields.
that anything we give ourselves to to be
able to get a return and be able to feed
our families has been cursed with a
measure of futility
and we will never again get 100% return
on the labor of our hands. There are no
100% workers
because of the built-in futility
and the curse that is work today. For
every employee you hire and hope to get
a 100% return, you won't. You'll only
ever get a 60% maybe a 70%.
Efficiency is lost across all industries
and labors of men and women because of
sick days off, because of public
holidays, because of stress in your
workers, because of attention drift,
because of faulty decisions that take
away from the organization, because of
misdirected energy, because of unengaged
workers. You never get 100% return
for this was a curse that was placed on
the man. Now all the books you read, all
the industry authors write books as
though we have finally cracked the code
on how to get 100% return from your
workers efficiency. But it's a lie.
And if your company in your company
you're trying to run the staff as though
they are to give back 100% return and
you have not built into your HR policies
and the way you run your staff but
expect 100% return on them, they will
only ever at their best give you maybe a
60 maybe a 70% return.
And if you push them, they count you to
be an evil employer.
You're a slave driver and they don't
enjoy your work. And there's a lot of
attrition which takes away again from
the efficiency that you hope to hold on
to. All you do is leave a trail of
damaged, burntout people who hate their
job and whose health you broke as you
tried to run them like machines.
This is exactly the case when it comes
to marriage. There is no more 100%
marriage. Marriage is broken
because of our sin.
And so I want us to listen to a song
together. And this song is called
um broken together. And it's a song
about marriage. I think what this singer
is saying is,
"If only we could both admit that we're
broken.
If only you could bring your shattered
dreams and I bring mine, then maybe,
just maybe, would last forever
because would know were broken and could
take it to the Lord to heal." I think
it's a beautiful and hopeful song.
Just like a parent who has a child who
is handicapped,
you love them as they are. You can't
change that reality. And so you love
them as they are and you adjust your
expectations
for them.
You extend grace and forgiveness.
In the same way you are broken
and your spouse is broken and your
marriage is broken
because we live in a world that has been
touched by sin. So extend grace and
forgiveness to them. Adjust your
expectations of them and let grace and
forgiveness abound.
This is what Jesus would say to you and
I in that situation in this reality.
I will not remove this brokenness that
was sin because my grace is sufficient
for you and my power is made perfect
in weakness.
Last week I had titled my message the
three reasons for which God created
marriage. And last week we talked about
that marriage from the book of Ephesians
chapter 5 is first and foremost a
testimony and a witness of Christ's love
for the church.
I want to move on to the second reason
this week and the second reason is this.
God created marriage for companionship,
for community, and for communial being.
When he created man in Genesis 2 26 and
27, this is what he said as he thought
through or desired to create man. He
said, "Let us make man in our own
image." And so he made them male and
female.
God
is plural and the words he used let us
not let me but let us make man in our
own image are plural words because God
is plural because he exists as God the
Father, God the Son, and God the Holy
Spirit. And in that trinity there is
community and there is companionship and
there is a sense of belonging together.
And this he wanted to create in mankind.
And it would have been our lot and our
blessing had we not sinned.
He is a plural god and so he created
woman. So what is companionship in
marriage then?
What then are we aspiring to hold on to
to become? I want to share an answer
with you that is a very personal answer
for me and a very practical answer and
in this sense then a very downto-earth
answer. This is me okay this isn't
everybody but this is me. Okay. In
December of 2021, at the end of the
year, I had taken time to go off on a
retreat as was uh my wife and my habit
to at the end of the year to go and sit
down together and to look into the new
year and to ask what will this year be
about to look into the past year and to
say this is what God has been doing. And
we would we had been doing this for a
long time. every year between the 25th
and the 1st would go away on retreat,
maybe leave the kids with an auntie or
something and just the two of us and we
would sit down and ask what have we
learned from God through the course of
this year and what do we need to learn
or what do we sense God is saying that
we need to learn and then we'd ask what
about our children and we'd say you know
this child is struggling with a sense of
fear u maybe a sense of hesitancy to
speak out when she needs needs to. And
so this year for this child, these are
the character qualities we're going to
work at building into the child. And
then this one has a different problem
altogether, maybe pride. And so we're
going to, you know, take time to be
working on those qualities and would
make map out our year's uh you know,
plans on that retreat. But this year in
2021, I was alone cuz my wife had had to
go somewhere else to attend to something
that was happening. and I I didn't need
to be there, but she needed to be there.
And so I was alone. And so I was having
a conversation with God. Same thing that
I was doing. And I was having a
conversation with God. And I asked him,
"Lord, where do you need to grow me? And
what does this next year look like? What
do you need me to know so that I can do
what you are desiring of me?" And I
asked a question. I told the question,
Lord, this is 2021. It's only a couple
of years back about four years, five
years back and I said, you know, um I'm
coming to the end of my runway. I'm
growing older. I don't have that many
years, you know, still left. I'm not 20s
anymore. So, as I come to the end of my
runway, I really want my marriage to
thrive.
And Lord, you know, been there, done
that. to have had all the arguments
about raising up kids and all the
disagreements about money and all the
you know you're working too hard you
shouldn't be at the office so late at
other times it's that you know I don't
like the food and I I don't want to eat
what is presented and all those
arguments that are young couples and
young marriage and I'm an old man now
and I don't want this to be the rest of
my life and married life and so I asked
the Lord please help me. I know I'm part
of that brokenness and part of that
problem. But please help me, Lord, to
elevate my marriage from mediocre to
this level where it's fulfilling and
enjoyable and something that I thrive
on. And God answered me by giving me two
passages in scripture. These were the
two passages. The first one was
Philippians chapter 2 2 through to
verse4. And because I was reading this
through the lens of marriage, I've added
those words into my reading of it now so
that you can understand what I sense God
was saying to me. Oscar, you want to
elevate your marriage into something
fulfilling, then this is what you will
need to do. I read the passage. Firstly,
be one in spirit and in mind.
In other words,
as a couple, work to be agreed in your
heart and in your mind on all that you
stand for together and all that you do
as a couple. Now, I'm an African man. My
father when he my father was a
businessman and a wealthy businessman
and uh we had seven cars in our drive.
We lived in Karen. We had seven cars and
one was an MG I think 1 Spitfire 1,500.
I mean it's a car for teenagers and this
is what my father drove drives you know
200 kilometers an hour or something. We
had seven cars. We had I think it was
three Volvos. um different you know age
and then there was a VW and etc. Seven
cars in the driveway and my father would
come home and my mother would see that
he's come with a new car
and there hadn't been a conversation and
my father would come home as the African
man he's he is and he'd say we bought a
car today.
That was the end of the matter.
I learned well from my father. I would
come home and tell my wife, "Oh, by the
way, we bought a 55 in TV today." There
was no consultation. There was no
budgeting. There was nothing. I was
being the African man I am. Okay? And
God says, "Be one in spirit and in mind.
Don't do anything before you're agreed
on it." Secondly, verse three, do
nothing out of selfish ambition or a
prideful attempt to advance yourself.
A third one was in humility value your
spouse above yourself. Be a servant to
your spouse. Consider your spouse with
high dignity as someone who needs to be
served and attended to in an honorable
way. And when he says do nothing out of
selfish ambition, in other words, don't
put yourself and your needs first.
Put the needs of your spouse first.
Think of ways you can serve her and
spoil her. And you know how sometimes
you read the Bible and you say to God, I
bas Lord, I'm done here. You know, this
this was enough. No more. You know, let
me move on. But there was a second
passage that he had prompted into my
mind. And I turned to it. And as I read
it, I'm reading the the living Bible uh
version of it, but I've added the words
in marriage just to give it context. And
this is what it says. If you speak in
the tongues of men or of angels, but do
not have love, then you are just a loud
and noisy gong.
And many of you as husbands here, myself
included, have been a loud and noisy
gong in the house.
And by the way, so too have the women.
It's not just the men. Okay?
If you have the gift of prophecy and can
understand all mysteries and special
knowledge and you have a faith that can
move mountains, but you do not have
love, then you gain nothing.
Doesn't profit you. It's useless.
In verse three, if you give all your
possessions to the poor and you give
over your body to suffering and to
hardship for Christ and to martyrdom,
but you do not have love, then you are
wasting your time. It's useless and you
gain nothing.
Love in marriage is very patient and
kind. It doesn't sit in the car hooting
for your spouse to hurry up or will be
late.
I can hear some women laughing. It's got
to be they know what I'm talking about
because guys, as a young husband, that
was me. When the children came,
I would get so irritated that we said
we're leaving at, you know, 2:00 cuz
we're going to visit a friend. It's now
2:20 and still the family has not come
out of the house. Me, I came out at 5
minutes to two and I sat in the car, put
my safety belt, but nobody has appeared
and I start hooting in irritation and
would have an argument about it. And my
wife would tell me, "If you want me to
come out on time, come and help me with
the kids.
[Laughter]
And I would say 2:00 is 2:00.
It goes on to say, "Love in marriage is
never jealous or envious, bragging about
how much you yourself have done and the
other one hasn't.
You keep telling me that I shouldn't
work in the office late, but I'm the one
who's bringing the money home so that we
can pay our bills and you keep telling
me that I work too hard and I'm in the
office too late. You don't even bring in
half what I bring in.
And by the way, I became a bishop in
time. It's that bad. Okay.
Love in marriage is never arrogant or
proud, contemptuous,
selfcentered,
showing a lack of respect for the other,
sneering or rude. Instead, love in
marriage is supportive and humble and
quick to uplift the other, kind and
affirming.
I know the first part of that
passage and the words given there. The
second part was a pipe dream. Love in
marriage does not demand its own way. It
does not shout down the other. It is not
irritable or touchy, easily offended.
Love in marriage does not hold grudges
and will hardly ever notice when the
other does it wrong.
If you love someone in marriage, you
will be loyal to them no matter what the
cost. If you love someone in marriage,
you will always believe in them. Always
know that they did their best and always
stand your ground in defending them.
This is what love in marriage looks
like.
B and I, my wife, have been married now
for 38 years.
When I remember that this girl
chose to be by my side
and gave up opportunities
in her life to pursue her own dreams and
her own way so that we could share life
together. I am in awe that anyone would
do that for me. That's how much she
loved me. This girl gave up career goals
so that we could make a home together.
This girl carried three pregnancies
so that she could give me children. This
girl went through labor three times
for my children. And this girl even
today looks after me and watches over me
and cooks for me and keeps home for me.
I am in awe at the woman that God gave
me as a companion.
Now God doesn't say I honor her because
she does these things for me. He says I
honor her because I chose her. I made a
vow to her and I made a covenant in the
presence of God and I am to do these
things
for God himself.
And so I said in that conversation with
the Lord, my years,
for years I have run my race hard, taken
that mountain, accomplished dreams,
but I have often taken her for granted.
And so help me Lord to love her the way
I should have been doing it all along. I
took these two passages in Philippians
chapter 2 and in 1 Corinthians chapter
13 and I tried to condense them into
something that will guide me in the way
that I treat my wife. And I distilled
for them four actions
that would be for me the standard and
the way that I show her love. I want to
share these with you. And this is me,
okay? This isn't you. This is me. Um,
but don't go and tell her cuz I've never
told her from 2021 that I'm doing four
things, okay? I'm not a very romantic
man. As you can see, it needs to be
mechanical, okay, and remembered. But I
I've never told her, but I do these four
things and it has changed my marriage. I
put them into an acronym that I call
axe. ACS
and the A stands for that I will adore
her daily.
To adore someone is to love and deeply
respect them. We say things like, "I
adored my mother when she was alive." We
say things like, "She has only one son
and she adors him." And we all know the
warm sentiments and emotions that
accompany adoration. Another English
word that you can interchange with the
word adore is a word worship. I worship
my mother.
I worship my wife. It's not the worship
I have for God. It's a different sort of
worship. But I adore her and I worship
her even as I do my God in heaven.
My adoration does not depend on me and
how I'm feeling. And it doesn't depend
on the hurtful words that was spoken
last night. And it doesn't depend on my
wife's response even to my adoration. My
adoration depends
on a commitment I have made that I will
love her this way.
And whether she responds to it or not, I
will adore my wife
because of the amazing woman that God
gave me.
My adoration is divorced even from the
hurtful brokenness that we sometimes
display to each other. Even today when
we speak rashly and we speak harshly and
we use the wrong tone, I will adore her.
And every morning when I get up,
I adore her. And it's often in words and
I will tell her of how amazing she is
and how glad that I married her. And for
guys, if you're as uncreative as I get,
I've got the perfect line for you. Try
it tomorrow morning. If your wife is not
here and tell her, "Sweetie, if I was to
get married again, I would choose you
all over again." Oh,
now if she's here, you have to find
other words. That one won't work. Okay.
But then the second word, the C stands
for cherish. That I will cherish her
daily. To cherish is to protect and to
care for lovingly. I cherish something
that is precious to me. To show
affection for the word sounds tender and
even warm.
And so I will often again message my
tenderness to her. Now I don't like you
know get up in the morning and okay I've
done the A now let's do the C and etc.
But in the day I will intermingle these
and look for opportunities to cherish my
wife and to celebrate her and to in this
sense then care for her lovingly. And it
may be you know that I can serve her
drink. Um I can serve her dessert. My
wife loves loves loves loves chocolate.
And so there is always a bountiful
supply of chocolates in our home for her
cuz I don't eat much chocolate at all.
And she loves loves loves loves flowers
cuz she's an artist. And so I'll often
go to the junction here and the the the
fruit shop there. Um they have beautiful
flower arrangements and I'll buy a big
bunch and I will take them home for her
and she loves them.
I will cherish her. Here's a third one.
The T stands for touch. I will touch her
daily.
Now, I'm not even talking about a sexual
touch. I'm talking just about touch that
when I go into the kitchen and she's
often there before me, I will go up to
her and just hug her for half a minute
and tell her I love her. When she comes
and asks me, you know, please help me do
my necklace. I can't quite get the
clasp, you know, in properly. I will do
that and then I will caress her and tell
her how beautiful she is. Now, you may
think, "Ah, this guy is romantic."
No, I'm not. I'm not.
I have to think about it before it
happens. I'm going downstairs and she's
already down there. What am I going to
do if I'm going to do this? It's not
about romance. It's about obedience.
Now don't tell her that.
But then the fourth one after touch is
the S which for me is about serving her
daily.
And so when she comes home with a car, I
will go to the car and say, "Is there
anything I can carry for you?" And I
will say things like, "Don't carry that
upstairs. You know that bag. Let me
carry it for you." And I will find other
ways to serve her constantly. Can I get
you a cup of tea? Can I get you a
dessert? Can I get you something to
drink? I will look for opportunity to
serve her. African man,
it can be done.
Miracles still happen.
And because I've never told her, they
don't come in an order. But I'm always
looking for ways and opportunities
to do these four things. And when I have
mastered these, then I will change them.
And maybe the T will be, you know, say
thank you. Maybe the S will be say
sorry. You know, maybe the A will be
affirm as opposed to adore, but to keep
doing these things that are the
expression of love as given to us in 1
Corinthians 13. And I kid you not, guys,
it has changed our affection for one
another in marriage.
And it is because I did it. I didn't ask
her to do it. But my doing it has caused
her to start reciprocating and doing the
same things back in return without even
knowing that she's doing what I have
planned and what she is now
spontaneously responding with. And our
marriage has grown and I really do
believe in the short runway that I have
that is possibly 20 years before I go to
be with the Lord. I want these to be the
years that I spoiled my wife to bits and
I loved her with every fiber of my
being.
Even as we grow older,
there's a saying I came across some time
back and it has become so true of me and
my love for my wife as I seek to move us
from mediocre
to the place where there is fulfillment
in our marriage. But what it means is
that I have to die to my own desires
daily and instead live for my wife and
serve her and cherish her and affirm
her. These are the words.
We're growing older as a couple.
We're both not the young beautiful girl
she was that I met at the age of 23. And
I'm not the young handsome man that she
met. Things have tended to droop.
But my love is not a matter of her looks
anymore. My love is a matter of the
commitment I have made to her and the
wonderful woman that she is. And so I
come back to the words of the song. If
only we could both admit that we're
broken. We're not perfect. If only we
could bring our shattered dreams
together, then maybe, just maybe, would
last forever because we know that we're
broken and can bring us, both of us, to
the Lord to heal.
Would you pray with me as we conclude?
Father, I know that there are many
marriages here
where one or both spouse long
to have a fulfilling marriage and not a
mediocre one,
but they feel stuck. Everything always
comes round into the latest disagreement
or argument
and the arguments are about everything
and there is no peace and no joy. I ask
Lord that for whoever it is who's here
today representing that marriage maybe
even both husband and wife are here
today that you would help them to come
to the place where they love with the
love of first Corinthians chapter 13
because of you not because of their
spouse that they do this in obedience to
you not because they're trying to woo
their spouse all over again and that you
would change their marriage by changing
them, not their spouse.
Give us the courage, Lord, to step onto
that plate,
and to believe that as we do this, you
can change our marriage
into something, even though fallen,
something that is fulfilling.
Oh father, help us.
Nobody wants to be in a marriage
that distresses them.
But we have to die to self to ever hope
that we could be in a marriage that
fulfills us. And we don't like dying.
So help us to learn what it means to die
to self. In Jesus' name we pray. Amen.
Amen. Thank you.